Guide to the Samuel J. Tilden papers, 1794-1886 [bulk 1835-1876]
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Samuel J. Tilden papers
1794-1886
1835-1876
MssCol 2993
2993
Tilden, Samuel J. (Samuel Jones), 1814-1886
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
42.78 linear feet 99 boxes, 13 volumes
Samuel J. Tilden (1814-1886) served as Governor of New York, 1875-1876, and was the Democratic nominee for the Presidency in 1876. Tilden began his career as a corporate lawyer; he served as Corporate Counsel for the City of New York, as a member of the New York State Assembly, and as Chairman of the Democratic National Convention. Monies from his estate contributed to the founding of The New York Public Library. His papers document his political and legal career and are comprised primarily of correspondence, political and legal files, financial documents, writings, speeches, and personal papers dating from 1785 - 1929 (bulk 1832 - 1886).
Samuel J. Tilden (1814-1886) served as Governor of New York, 1875-1876, and was the Democratic nominee for the Presidency in 1876. Tilden began his career as a corporate lawyer; he served as Corporate Counsel for the City of New York, as a member of the New York State Assembly, and as Chairman of the Democratic National Convention. Monies from his estate contributed to the founding of The New York Public Library.
Born in New Lebanon, New York, in 1814, Tilden was the 5th son of Elam Tilden, a shopkeeper, pharmacist, and postmaster prominent in Democratic politics. Samuel showed a precocious interest in politics, and through his father, made the acquaintance of Martin Van Buren, who would later become a friend and supporter. Van Buren encouraged Tilden's burgeoning political aspirations, and he developed a reputation as a skilled writer and speechmaker by his early twenties.
Tilden first entered public office in 1843, at the age of 27, when he was appointed Corporation Counsel for the City of New York. His candidacy received support from the network of Democratic Party members he had cultivated since his earliest days in politics, and he won the nomination by 20 out of 26 votes. However, his tenure was short-lived; in 1844, Mayor James Harper took office and removed individuals he deemed hostile to his administration. Tilden ran unsuccessfully for the office of Attorney General in 1855.
Throughout the 1850s and 1860s, Tilden largely took leave of politics to focus on his legal career. His practice proved both popular and lucrative, although he took many cases pro bono. A shrewd businessman as well as a skilled lawyer, Tilden excelled particularly in the field of corporate law. Among his well-known cases are the defense of the Pennsylvania Coal Company against the Delaware & Hudson Canal Company; the complaint of the Cumberland Coal & Iron Company against its board of directors; the contested 1856 election for state comptroller between John S. Giles and Azariah C. Flagg; the Cunningham-Burdell murder case in 1857; and a subsequent related suit over Dr. Burdell's estate
In the years leading up to the Civil War, the Wilmot Proviso on the prohibition of slavery in newly-acquired territories proved a hot-button issue for the Democratic Party, ultimately leading to a schism between the conservative "Hunkers" and the radical "Barnburners." Tilden, along with Martin and John Van Buren, supported the Barnburners, and assisted in composing the Barnburner Address repudiating the nomination of Lewis Cass as the Democratic candidate for the presidency. The Barnburners allied themselves with Whigs and Abolitionists to form the Free-Soil Party, which ran Martin Van Buren as a third-party candidate and defeated Cass.
Tilden had been elected to the New York State Assembly in 1846, and returned to the legislature in 1872. He used his position to take on corruption in state government, most notably through the impeachment of New York State Supreme Court Justices George G. Barnard, Albert Cardozo, and John H. McCunn. This, coupled with his investigation into corruption within the U.S. Customs House, presaged Tilden's most notable political achievement: the exposure and prosecution of the Tweed Ring.
William M. "Boss" Tweed was a fixture in New York State and Tammany Hall politics from the 1850s until his death in 1878. His first recorded act of misconduct, the bribery of an election supervisor, took place in 1858, and by 1859 he had become Grand Sachem of the most powerful political machine in the nation. In 1870, he was appointed commissioner of public works, and the influence of his "Ring" began to spread. With the assistance of Parks Commissioner Peter B. Sweeney, Controller Richard B. Connelly, and Mayor A. Oakey Hall, Tweed was able to exert enormous control over city politics -- as well as taxpayer funds-- through bribery, embezzlement, and kickbacks. When Tweed introduced a new city charter which would further consolidate the Ring's power, Tilden, as chairman of the Democratic State Committee, denounced him and began a pitched battle to disable the Ring and end Tweed's corrupt practices. Canvassing the banks where Tweed and his cohorts passed checks and held accounts, Tilden analyzed the finances of the Ring, and obtained legal proof its malfeasance, bringing an end to one of the most corrupt political administrations in the history of the United States.
Tilden's successful prosecution of the Tweed Ring and service in the State Assembly paved the way for his nomination as the Democratic candidate for Governor in 1874 against respected Republican incumbent Gen. John A. Dix. Tilden won the popular vote by a margin of 50,000. His work in exposing fraud in the state canal system furthered his reputation as a reform-minded governor and an outspoken opponent of political corruption, and increased his popularity with the public at large. However, his reform efforts were often hampered by antagonism from the Republican majority in the State Legislature.
Tilden served as a delegate to the 1864 and 1868 Democratic National Conventions, and as New York Democratic State Chair from 1872-1882. Having demonstrated his skills as a reformer, he easily won the Democratic nomination for the presidency in 1876. He won the popular vote and collected 184 electoral votes to 165 for Republican candidate Rutherford B. Hayes. 20 electoral votes remained uncounted and in dispute. After these votes were awarded to Hayes -- thus giving him the election -- Tilden and the Democratic Party went to great lengths to uncover evidence of fraud in the Electoral College. Ultimately, Tilden conceded the election.
Tilden was proposed as a potential Democratic candidate in 1880 and again in 1884, but declined both times, citing poor health. He soon withdrew from public service, though he remained a confidant and advisor to many of his fellows.
He died at Graystone, his country house in Yonkers, on August 4, 1886. In the years following his death, a bitter struggle over his estate ensued between his trustees and his heirs-at-law over the provision of the will that the bulk of the estate be used for the creation of a free library and reading room in New York City. The free library was ultimately established, and later became The New York Public Library.
The bulk of the collection was recieved from the Tilden Estate and Trust between 1903 and 1930 at the direction of John Bigelow, Andrew H. Green, and George W. Smith, executors of the Tilden Estate. Tilden's trustees and executors were "empowered to burn and destroy any of [my] letters, papers, or other documents, whether printed or in manuscript, which in their judgment will answer no useful purpose to preserve." New York State historian and Tilden biographer Alexander C. Flick noted in 1939 that the papers had been "carefully sifted four times by the executors to exclude everything derogatory to Tilden." The collection was open for use for many decades before being formally accessioned by the Manuscripts Division in 1986 by Charles Kronick. The papers were fully processed in 2009 by Kit Messick
The Samuel J. Tilden papers, dating from 1785 - 1929 (bulk 1832 - 1886), emphasizes Tilden's public life and works rather than his private life. Correspondence comprises a significant portion of the collection as a whole, reaching from his student days through his death in 1886, and following the arc of his career from student to veteran politician. Family correspondence focuses on his father, Elam, and on his nephew, Col. William Tilden Pelton. The General correspondence represents a full roster of political, social, and financial luminaries, and covers an extensive range of topics. The legal series contains case files and related material illustrating the highlights of Tilden's legal career, while his stint as Counsel for the Corporation is documented in a limited fashion through official documentation of violations of city ordnances.
Tilden's activities with the Democratic Republican Party and Free-Soil movement are given little coverage. His efforts to curb political corruption are presented in the New York State Assembly files, and the fall of the Tweed Ring is recorded through financial and legal documentation. Gubernatorial files relate to his executive and legislative activities, and contain reports, statistics, petitions, and drafts of assembly bills. The prosecution of the Canal Ring receives particular attention. The contested Presidential Election of 1876 does not receive significant coverage beyond Tilden's correspondence with his confederates, and in the records of voting returns from the Electoral College.
Tilden often maintained multiple iterations of his written works and speeches, although this collection is not a definitive record of his writings. Many manuscript drafts and revisions have been preserved, but some works are represented only by published reprints.
Tilden's personal papers contain little to illuminate his life or interests outside the political sphere. Material consists predominantly of financial and legal documents, and a small quantity of school work and juvenilia. Family papers contain early deeds and printed matter dating prior to Tilden's birth, but are mainly comprised of genealogical research.
The Samuel J. Tilden papers are organized in the following series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1810 - 1919, n.d.
Series II. Counsel of the Corporation, 1839 - 1844, n.d.
Series III. Legal Files, 1832 - 1891, n.d.
Series IV. Democratic Republican party and Free-Soil movement, 1832 - 1853, n.d.
Series V. Democratic National Committee, 1868 - 1872
Series VI. Tweed Ring, 1868 - 1875
Series VII. New York State Assembly, 1872 - 1873, n.d.
Series VIII. Gubernatorial files, 1864 - 1877, n.d.
Series IX. Presidential election of 1876, 1876 - 1878
Series X. Writings and Speeches, ca. 1820s - 1886, n.d.
Series XI. Personal papers, 1785 - 1929
Received from the Tilden Estate and Trust with additional purchases.
Elizabeth Ogilvy Benger note. Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
Alexander Clarence Flick papers, ca. 1830-1938. Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
Bryant-Godwin papers, 1804-1913, bulk. Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
George Bancroft papers, 1823-1890.. Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
John Bigelow papers, 1839-1912.. Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
Tilden Trust records, 1878-1938.. Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library.
Bigelow, John, 1817-1911; Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878; Dana, Charles A. (Charles Anderson), 1819-1897; Manning, Daniel; Marble, Manton, 1834-1917; Seymour, Horatio, 1810-1886; Tweed, William Marcy, 1823-1878; Weed, Smith M.; Canals -- New York (State); Canals -- Pennsylvania; Elections -- United States; Political parties -- United States; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1876; Railroads -- United States; Subways -- New York (State) -- New York; Tweed Ring; Architectural drawings; Blueprints; Maps; Photoprints; Delaware and Hudson Canal (N.Y. and Pa.); New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- To 1898; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Governors; Lawyers; Politicians; Presidential candidates
- Series I. Correspondence, 1810 - 1919, n.d.; 38247; 35 boxes, 14.5 linear feet
  This series, the largest and most comprehensive in the collection, includes Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, and Subject Files generated throughout the course of Tilden's legal and political career. The vast majority of the correspondence relates to his professional life. The General Correspondence is strong in documentation of Tilden's political career, but contains few insights into his personal life. Representation of Tilden's term as Counsel of the Corporation is limited to one folder. Tweed Ring material covers Tilden's investigation into the corrupt political machine through communications with colleagues, bankers, and members of the Ring. New York State Assembly Correspondence is notable for its coverage of the impeachment of New York State Supreme Court judges. Gubernatorial Correspondence includes material relating to the dismantling of the Canal Ring, material relating to state legislation, and a significant quantity of letters from Tilden's constituents. Subject files refer to files of correspondence segregated by Tilden relating to specific topics, such as canals and coastal defense.
  - I. A. Family, 1810 - 1886, n.d.; 38248
    Family correspondence dates from 1810, prior to Tilden's birth, and continues through his death in 1886. His close relationships with family members are evident in the Family Correspondence, though this material tends to specifically reflect Tilden's youth and early adulthood. Letters between Samuel and his father, Elam, and between Samuel and his brother Moses are prevalent; also included are letters from other siblings, aunts and cousins. Of particular note is a folder of correspondence belonging to Tilden's nephew, Col. William Tilden Pelton. Appointed by his uncle to the position of military secretary during Tilden's term as governor, and later to the management of his presidential campaign, Pelton fell from grace during the vote-buying scandal of the "cipher dispatch conspiracy." The Pelton folder contains letters exchanged with Tilden, as well as with individuals involved in Tilden's and Pelton's political career in the 1860s and 1870s. Lastly, this series contains some drafts of Tilden's outgoing letters, though the recipients of these letters are not identified, and many exist only in fragmented form.
    - Barnes, Henrietta, 1833 - 1834; 38249 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barnes, Julia, 1834 - 1839, n.d.; 38250 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Barnes, Parthenia, 1832 - 1844, n.d.; 38251 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Doubleday, Cynthia, 1828, 1847; 38252 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jones, John Patterson, 1832, 1841 - 1846; 38253 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pelton, Mary B. (Tilden), 38254
      - 1832 - 1850, 1884, n.d., 292045 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - undated, 292046 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pelton, William Tilden, 1861 - 1878, n.d.; 38255 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Tilden, Caroline M., 1882; 38256 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Tilden, Elam, 38257
      - 1810-1830, 292047 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 1832, 292048 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - 1833, 292049 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 1834 Jan - Jun, 292050 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - 1834 Jul - Dec, 292051 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - 1835, 292052 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 1836 Jan - Apr, 292053 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 1836 May - Dec, 292054 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 1837 Jan - Apr, 292055 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 1837 May - Dec, 292056 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 1838, 292057 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 1839 Jan - Jun, 292058 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 1839 Jul - Dec, undated circa 1830s, 292059 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 1840 Jan - Apr, 292060 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 1840 May - Dec, 292061 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 1841 Jan - Apr, 292062 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 1841 May - Dec, 292063 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 1842, 292064 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - undated, 292065 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Tilden, George F., 1832 - 1835; 38260 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Tilden, George H., 1884, 1891; 38261 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Tilden, Henrietta, 1830, 1835 - 1839, n.d; 38262 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Tilden, Henry A., 38263
      - 1832-1885, 292066 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - undated, 292067 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Tilden, J.B., 1838, 1844; 38264 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Tilden, Mary, 1883; 38265 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Tilden, Moses Younglove, 38266
      - 1832-1839, 292068 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - 1840-1843, 292069 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 1844-1869, 292070 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - undated, 292071 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Tilden, Polly Younglove (Jones), 1833 - 1852, n.d.; 38268 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Tilden, Samuel D., 1876; 38269 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Tilden, Samuel J. - unidentified drafts, 38270
      - 1833 - 1846, 292072 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 1852-1883, 292073 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - undated, 292074 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Tilden, Samuel Jones Junior, 1885 - 1886; 38271 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Tylden, Elanore, undated; 38272 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Tylden, Harriet, 1878, 1881 - 1886; 38273 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Tylden, Richard, 1884; 38274 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Tylden, William, 1884; 38275 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Ward, Henry Dana Artemas, 1841 - 1876; 38276 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - West, M.P., 1835 - 1836; 38277 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Younglove, Polly Patterson, 1835, 1843, n.d; 38278 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified aunt, 1832 - 1846, n.d.; 38279 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - I. B. General, 1830 - 1919, n.d.; 38280
    General correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name. The bulk of the correspondence dates from the height of Tilden's public career in the 1860s through the 1880s. Not surprisingly, it emphasizes Tilden's political connections through exchanges with local power brokers, state party members, and national representatives. Tilden's social relations are documented through his correspondence with William Cullen Bryant, Montgomery Blair, Charles A. Dana, Abram S. Hewitt, Francis Kernan, Daniel Manning, Daniel Magone, Manton Marble, Charles O'Conor, Samuel J. Randall, Dean Richmond, Horatio Seymour, and John and Martin Van Buren. Correspondence and letterpress books belonging to George W. Smith, Tilden's confidential secretary from 1866 until his death, are also notable for their scope, and contain many letters and responses written by Smith on Tilden's behalf.
    Tilden communicated regularly with New York City mayors Fernando Wood, John T. Hoffman, A.Oakey Hall (later vilified by Tilden as a member of the Tweed Ring), William F. Havemeyer, William Wickham, and others. Exchanges with Democratic National Committee chair August Belmont; with fellow New York State Assembly members Smith M. Weed and William B. Ogden; and with New York State Lieutenant Governors William Dorsheimer and Allen C. Beach are all notable representations of Tilden's affiliation with New York politicians, as are his communications with his predecessors in Albany, Governors Silas Wright, Horatio Seymour, and John A. Dix.
    The activities of Tammany Hall, of which Tilden was a longstanding member, are documented both prior to and following the Tweed Ring scandal through mailings and circulars, as well as through correspondence with Grand Sachems Isaac Vanderbuck Fowler, John Morrissey, John "Honest John" Kelly, and Augustus Schell. Also included in the General Correspondence files are letters to and from Tammany members who would later fall into disgrace, including Peter B. Sweeney, Richard Connolly, and William M. "Boss" Tweed himself.
    As Tilden's career advanced beyond the New York arena, his political network extended to include figures of national prominence, including Democratic National Committee Chair Robert M. McLane and delegate Benjamin F. Butler; U.S. Secretary of the Treasury Hugh McCullough, U.S. Secretary of War Daniel S. Lamont; U.S. Attorney General Jeremiah Black; Senator William Bigler; and William Maxwell Evarts, who served as counsel to Rutherford B. Hayes during the election of 1876. During the years of Reconstruction, Tilden also corresponded regularly with Union Army Generals-cum-politicians George B. McClellan, Henry Warner Slocum, and Wager Swayne.
    Tilden's long-standing association with his fellow lawyers and jurists are reflected in his correspondence with his law partner Nelson J. Waterbury; his predecessor in the New York State Assembly Amasa Parker; American Bar Association president William Allen Butler; Attorney General Edwards Pierrepont; Supreme Court Justice Noah Haynes Swayne; and his compatriot in the prosecution of the Tweed Ring, Wheeler H. Peckham.
    Many industrialists known to Tilden through his financial endeavors are present in this series, including S.L.M Barlow, Peter Cooper, Azariah C. Flagg (whom Tilden represented both in corporate and political lawsuits), Jay Gould, Abram S. Hewitt, Howard Potter, merchant seaman Robert B. Minturn, and Henry Fox Taintor, Tilden's "partner in war" on the Tammany Ring.
    A respected writer and orator, Tilden cultivated relationships with a number of distinguished authors and journalists, including Poultney Bigelow, Anthony Bleecker, George Ticknor Curtis, Horace Greeley, Louise Livingston Hunt, Joseph Pulitzer, and economist David A. Wells, whose views on taxation informed Tilden's own assessments on the subject. Other prominent figures appearing in Tilden's correspondence include epicurean and lobbyist Samuel Cutler Ward; charity worker Louisa Lee Schuyler, inventor Samuel F. B. Morse, and his socialite daughter Leila Morse Rummel.
    Additional letters from many of Tilden's political compatriots may be found elsewhere in the General Correspondence series, particularly within the Tweed Ring, New York State Assembly, and Gubernatorial correspondence. These files were maintained separately from the General correspondence files.
    - Abbett, Leon, 1884; 38281 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Abbott, Frank, 1874; 38282 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Abbot, Fred K., 1885 - 1886; 38283 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Abbot, J. G., 1875 -1878; 38284 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Abbry, R., 1868; 38285 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - The Academy of Music, 1879; 38286 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Adams, Charles Francis, 1876 - 1877; 38287 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Adams, Henry, 1883; 38288 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Adams, John Quincy, 1868; 38289 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Agan, A. H., 1855, 1875; 38290 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Agnew, John T., 1839 - ca. 1846; 38291 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Airlie (first name unknown), 1864, 1868; 38292 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Aleshire, Charles C., 1877; 38293 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Alexander, Henry M., 1876; 38294 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Alfred, Frank H., 1880; 38295 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Allen, Ethan A., 1876; 38296 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Allen, Horatio, 1849; 38297 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Allen, Stephen, 1846; 38298 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Allen, William F., 1849, 1864 - 1872; 38299 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Alley, John P., 1875; 235468 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Alley, Saul, 1846; 38300 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Alwood, Thomas G., 1855, 1875; 38301 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Ames, Oakes, 1867 - 1872; 38302 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Anderson, Charles E., 1842; 38303 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Andrews, J.D., 1861; 38304; Transcription only (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Andrews, W. C., 1875; 38305 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Andrus, J.D., 1861, 1876; 38306 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Angel, B.F., 1848, 1875; 38307 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Apgar, Edgar K., 1874 - 1882; 38308 (Box 5, Folder 29)